<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../SIMP_Documentation.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;]>

<chapter id="ch-sc-System_Management">
  <chapterinfo>
    <title id="ch-sc-System_Management-title">Information System Management</title>
    <affiliation>
      <orgname>SIMP Team</orgname>
    </affiliation>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>SIMP</keyword>
      <keyword>Security</keyword>
      <keyword>Secure</keyword>
      <keyword>Framework</keyword>
      <keyword>Puppet</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>
  <title>Information System Management</title>
  <para>
   This chapter contains SIMP security concepts that are related to the 
   management security controls in 
  <ulink url="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsSPs.html">NIST 800-53</ulink>.
  </para>
  <section id="Risk_Assessment">
    <title>Risk Assessment</title>
    <para>
     This section describes the process of identifying risks within
     a system.
    </para>
    <section id="SIMP_Risk_Assessment">
      <title>SIMP Self Risk Assessment</title>
      <para>
       Risk can be found in any system. The SIMP team is constantly 
       evaluating the system and the settings to minimize inherit risk. 
       Most risks can be mitigated by processes and procedures at the 
       implementation level. The following table describes the known 
       areas in SIMP. [RA-1]
      </para>
      <para>
      <table frame="all">
          <title>SIMP Risk</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Risk</entry>
                <entry>Possible Mitigations</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Disabling Puppet:</emphasis>
                This can cause the clients to be out of sync with the Puppet 
                Master.</entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                   SIMP attempts to force a break on any locks and restart 
                   Puppet on all clients after a time of 4*runinterval (30 minutes 
                   by default). Implementations should ensure that further steps 
                   have not been taken to disable Puppet and should monitor their 
                   logs. Administrators can use the <emphasis role="bold">puppetlast</emphasis> 
                   command on the Puppet Master to detect servers that have not 
                   checked in within a reasonable time period.
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                <para>
                 <emphasis role="bold">Out of Date Patches:</emphasis> SIMP 
                 can be built with the RPMs from CentOS or Red Hat. Those RPMs 
                 should be assumed out of date at the time a system is initially 
                 installed (if using the SIMP DVD).
                </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                <para>
                 Implementations should obtain the latest RPMs and apply 
                 them in a reasonable manner.
                </para>
                <para>
                 All SIMP systems will, by default, attempt to update 
                 all packages using YUM nightly. Therefore, having an updated 
                 repository will ensure that the systems are updated on a 
                 regular basis.
                </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Poor Account Management:</emphasis>  
                SIMP security access control is based on users being created 
                and managed over time. Giving shell access to unnecessary users allows 
                them the opportunity to escalate privileges.</entry>
                <entry>Use the default LDIFs and local user modules to ensure that
                account settings remain restrictive. Ensure the system has policies 
                and procedures in place to manage accounts. Finally, ensure that users 
                are in appropriate groups with limited privileges.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="Vulnerability_Scanning">
      <title>Vulnerability Scanning</title>
      <para>
       The SIMP development and security team performs regular vulnerability 
       scanning of the product using commercial and open source tools. Results 
       and mitigations for findings from those tools can be provided upon request. 
       [CA-2, RA-5]
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="Assessment_Authorization">
    <title>Security Assessment and Authorization</title>
    <para>
     Assessment and authorization varies by implementation. Implementations are 
     encouraged to use documentation artifacts provided by the SIMP team to 
     assist with assessment and authorization. [CA-2]
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
