<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../SIMP_Documentation.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="ch-os-OpenStack_Integration">
  <chapterinfo>
    <title id="ch-os-OpenStack_Integration-title">OpenStack Integration</title>
    <affiliation>
      <orgname>SIMP Team</orgname>
    </affiliation>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>OpenStack In SIMP - IceHouse</keyword>
      <keyword>Deployment</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <itermset>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>OpenStack In SIMP - IceHouse</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Deployment</primary>
      </indexterm>
    </itermset>
  </chapterinfo>
  <title>OpenStack Integration</title>
  <para>
    This chapter explains how to integrate OpenStack IceHouse in the SIMP environment.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>OpenStack In SIMP - IceHouse</title>
      <para>
        OpenStack is a collection of IaaS cloud computing services aimed at creating
        a free and open source platform for cloud development and deployment.  It is
        designed in a modular fasion, encompassing the following components:
      </para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Cinder </emphasis>Block Storage Service</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Glance </emphasis>VM Image Service</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Keystone </emphasis>Identity Service</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Nova </emphasis>Compute Service</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Horizon </emphasis>Dashboard Service</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Neutron </emphasis>Networking Service</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Swift </emphasis>Object Storage Service</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Ceilometer </emphasis>Metrics</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Heat </emphasis>Templating</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        Integration of OpenStack into SIMP provides an easily scalable, secture cloud
        infrastructure for the end user.  Currently, SIMP supports OpenStack IceHouse for 
        CentOS 6.5, with the exception of Swift.
      </para>
      <para>
       Each OpenStack module has been encapsulated into SIMP as a Puppet module, for
       rapid deployment.  The following modules have been integrated into SIMP for
       OpenStack support:<emphasis role="bold"> Puppetlabs Apache, Cinder, Glance, INIFile, Keystone,
       MYSQL, Nova, Qpid, Horizon, Memcached, OpenVSwitch, Heat, Ceilometer, Neutron, and OpenStack.</emphasis>
      </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Deployment</title>
      <para>
        The premise of OpenStack deployment is to create a matrix of control and compute
        nodes.  The control nodes retain all identity, network, database, and
        communication services; compute nodes run virtualization services.
      </para>
      <para>
        Each OpenStack SIMP puppet module provides, for itself, the necessary configuration
        and security required to run inside SIMP.  All OpenStack modules are abstracted
        inta a single module, called 'openstack'.  This module contains pre-loaded
        configurations for OpenStack deployment, including the framework for basic control
        and compute nodes.
      </para>
      <para>
        Please note that each OpenStack puppet module (keystone, glance, cinder, nova, etc.)
        can run independent of the supplied 'openstack' module and manifests.  That
        means you, the end user, can opt to use the example manifests directly or not
        at all.  Create your own manifests for specific site deployments.
      </para>
      <para>
        To deploy, you must install the pupmod-puppetlabs-openstack module (which will chain-install all
        dependencies).  /etc/puppet/modules/openstack/simp has example hieradata yaml files for compute
        and control nodes.
      </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
